[SPEAKER_03]: We could talk about motivation.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just the fact that, like, motivation changes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Kind of starting your approach to dhamma with, like, this fanatical attitude.
[SPEAKER_03]: The same way you would get really into any other worldly activity.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, you take on the precepts, you start training in it, and you actually start trying to undo the tendency that is behind that motivation for things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, you find yourself, like, still focusing on your virtue and your conduct.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then, that, eh...
[SPEAKER_03]: That attitude, where it's like, you know, but I'm actually thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, it's not, you know, I'm not passionate about it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, I should be.
[SPEAKER_04]: And also, I should give up passion.
[SPEAKER_04]: You mean, like, feeling that you don't have enough motivation compared to when you started out, like, or that it might feel that way?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, compared to what you were used to as motivation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, like, because... Also, like, the idea that you might need to replace it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the only motivation that you know is not actually very helpful.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you mean that you realize... That you need a new type of motivation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, but the thing is that it's not... it's not up to you to, like,
[SPEAKER_04]: To replace it with something else, it's when, precisely, if you take on virtue, you keep the precepts, and then, the motivation that existed on account of your sensual activities, which is really that, like what you said, that kind of passionate, almost obsessive impulse, that's going to have to fade, because that depended on the type of activities that are against the precepts.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's why, in a way, it's fine if, starting out, a person feels like they're obsessed with the dhamma and they're like, kind of, really... because you would read that sutta where it says monks, you shouldn't cling to the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_04]: You should let it go like a raft, like you get to the other shore.
[SPEAKER_04]: But the thing is, people start saying that when they have a demon.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, they just got on the boat, like, the first second.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, immediately, like, okay, so, I should let go of the boat now.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you're still not even one centimeter away from the... from the near shore.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you have to... it's not up to you.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a... it's like, you would... you... it's when you directly recognize that the motivation, the energy that you have towards practice, that presents itself as motivation towards dhamma,
[SPEAKER_04]: You see for yourself, not that somebody else told you or something, you see for yourself, this is now taking me away from the actual cessation of craving.
[SPEAKER_04]: But from that beginning point of view, being passionate about dhamma and really kind of firing yourself up to keep the precepts and not give in to sensuality and abandon wholesome things, that is closer to the cessation of craving than if you
[SPEAKER_04]: You have less craving when you do that, than if you were to say like, oh, well, there's nothing to attain, so we just don't attach to anything, even to the dhamma, as a complete beginner who doesn't even have a good view.
[SPEAKER_04]: That would... that might feel from somebody's initial ideas about what peace is, that might feel better, but that's precisely because it's the path of least resistance and you're still fundamentally maintaining the same tendencies, like you said, the same... you're still going with the grain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, the wrong kind of indifference.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, like equanimity of just
[SPEAKER_04]: It's going to be circumstantial as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, it's going to be... if a person feels that, without keeping the precepts, without having gone through that process of, um... Restraints?
[SPEAKER_04]: No, well, but that process of feeling, like, almost, um... in a way, you could say, obsessed with restraint and abandoning the wrong things that they used to do.
[SPEAKER_04]: Without going through that process, if a person feels that they're equanimous,
[SPEAKER_04]: And that they're kind of able to be at peace and not be affected by things.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's only because they still have suitable conditions around them that don't disturb them too much.
[SPEAKER_04]: The only way that you would be actually equanimous and unmoved by things, not based on circumstances, not based on comforts, not based on what the Buddha called the pleasure of the household life,
[SPEAKER_04]: which are not limited to lay people.
[SPEAKER_04]: As a monk, if you still have that dependence on external comforts, those are the pleasures of lay life, as the Buddha called them.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, yeah, it's only through going through that training that initially might feel unpleasant or it might even feel
[SPEAKER_04]: The mind might even try to convince you that it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, you know, you should be... you shouldn't be, like, so... caring so much about something.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it's like, okay, well, you have cancer.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can choose to not really care, and live and enjoy each day as it passes, and not really worry about what's going to happen.
[SPEAKER_04]: The fact that you have a terminal illness that might kill you in any moment.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or, you can really see the fact of having cancer as a problem, and for the time being, let's say, be in a state of more agitation, but actually be doing something that might save your life, instead of just letting go in that kind of very early, premature way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, giving up craving, based on craving, which appears in the sutras somewhere, that's valid, but in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, based on that, at some point, you realize, wait, it's actually because of this same craving, that I now recognize as the origin of suffering, then it doesn't apply anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, but then that has to happen on its own.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not that you start, like, second-guessing yourself.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, oh, maybe my effort is...
[SPEAKER_04]: If that's what you feel effort is, if that's what is the direction of effort that you know, well, that's the least wrong thing for you to do at that time.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, only when it becomes apparent why it's inaccurate, then you'll be able to upgrade it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Otherwise, you're just acting out of a sense of duty or a sense of external reasoning or whatever you might have heard is the right level of effort.
[SPEAKER_04]: But for you, factually, whatever craving you experience, whatever defilements you experience, whatever for you stands for not giving in to that, is the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so it is by understanding what craving is, that all of that undergoes a change.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you cannot now say, oh, it's time for me now to start abandoning that craving which I originally had.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you will be making that choice based on some craving which you then don't see.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you would also be going back to things that you should have given up.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because that's usually what it means to say like, oh, I'm gonna relax.
[SPEAKER_04]: When you're too loose,
[SPEAKER_04]: You've not actually reached the right level of tightness and you start loosening.
[SPEAKER_04]: What it usually means is, yeah, you go back to things that are actually obstructions.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's more like everybody starts out too loose.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like it's... there's no way around it.
[SPEAKER_04]: You have to tighten it up.
[SPEAKER_04]: You have to take on that, again, even if it feels painful, that determination to
[SPEAKER_04]: Do not act out.
[SPEAKER_04]: Give up unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_04]: Purify your mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, inevitably, that will result in going, let's say, farther than where the middle way is.
[SPEAKER_04]: But then, when you reach that point, and you feel like... you actually see, like, oh, wait.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why am I winding myself up?
[SPEAKER_04]: Unnecessarily.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, past this point, there's already nothing unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, why am I constantly kind of trying to push things away farther than that?
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not necessary.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, then you realize, okay, so this is where I need to stay.
[SPEAKER_04]: Instead of here, you move back here, which means you're still keeping the precepts, you're still restraining your senses, you're still restraining your speech, but you're not
[SPEAKER_04]: Finding problems with everything and nothing.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're not saying, like, um... No, it's based on something internal.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, it's... now that's going to be based on something internal, because you have that direct...
[SPEAKER_04]: Recognition of these mental states that were driving you to go too far.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you see, oh, that was the problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not the, like, the external... Yeah, it's not, you know, it's not even the external level of renunciation, because in some suttas, the Buddha would talk about how
[SPEAKER_04]: In monks in general, like doing ascetic practices, and he would say, like for some people, that would be their way of practicing the Middle Way.
[SPEAKER_04]: In other words, it would not be excessive asceticism, because it's not based on the external activities that you're doing.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's whether internally you were just pushing with that sense of duty towards these external ideals of renunciation,
[SPEAKER_04]: Or whether you actually see the mind, you actually see its inclinations, and you're simply refraining from giving in to that.
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't think in terms of, oh, I should do this every day, or I should never do that every day, apart from the precepts.
[SPEAKER_04]: You just think in terms of, is there greed?
[SPEAKER_04]: Is there aversion?
[SPEAKER_04]: Is there delusion?
[SPEAKER_04]: Do I act out of it or not?
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, yes, for some that might result in doing a set of practices, but if you start doing these things, and you think that that's all that the practice is, just keep going as far as you can in that direction, limit more, restrict more, abandon more on that external level,
[SPEAKER_04]: You're not even allowing that room to become aware that, oh, wait, this is going too far now.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're responding like a... the mind kind of shows its thoughts, then you notice its desire, its desires, and then you are refraining from those desires, rather than
[SPEAKER_02]: Rather than restraining something, first, to then get a reaction from the mind, like a prototype.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it could be both, actually, depending.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, the thing is, like, if you're already looking for where the mind is, that's already a step forward.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, usually, that's not what happens.
[SPEAKER_04]: What happens is that you have these abstract notions, that certain things are always rooted in craving.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, based on that, you start giving things up, and then,
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, that's inevitably how you start out, because the precepts are just these specific things that you don't do, and you don't see for yourself where the craving behind those activities would be.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, at least, if you were instructed rightly, you would be making the effort to see, oh, actually, this is about the mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not about my mind, specifically.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, like, not even that for everyone the same things will be unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_04]: Again, apart from the precepts.
[SPEAKER_04]: For you, doing
[SPEAKER_04]: At that specific time, doing one thing could mean acting out of greed, acting out of aversion.
[SPEAKER_04]: For somebody else, it isn't.
[SPEAKER_04]: But then, acting out of these external notions of what's right and what's wrong, you might even think, oh, look at him.
[SPEAKER_04]: He's being indulged right now.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because you see it all on that level of, like... Like I always say, almost like a list.
[SPEAKER_04]: Things that you think are inappropriate and things that are appropriate.
[SPEAKER_04]: And if you start looking at your mind, you realize and recognizing your mind, you realize that's actually quite a burden to have to adhere to these almost like external guidelines.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's completely divorced.
[SPEAKER_04]: from the basis of where the hindrances actually are.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, which means you're acting out of them.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you're not seeing them, you're acting out of them automatically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, conformity to something external
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not what the actual virtue is.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even though, for most people, it may start like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's the right thing, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: those seven precepts that we were talking about recently, that still starts out as external.
[SPEAKER_01]: But to conform to that cannot be equated with being virtuous.
[SPEAKER_01]: The virtue begins when keeping those precepts shows you where your mind is pushing you and then you don't get in.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so it's like...
[SPEAKER_04]: It's kind of like... if you make the right effort on the basis of even taking on the precepts semi-blindly, let's say, just, okay, I just don't do these things, but you actually make the effort to
[SPEAKER_04]: See why those things are wrong.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, you would see the same thread underlies a whole bunch of other things that some people might think are fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: Some monks might think are fine because, because, you know, it's not explicitly stated in the vinaya or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're still taking that external thing as a criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it's really your own notions, like, kind of, almost like making inferences.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's completely like... That's why, from that point of view, it will always be subjective.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then people will be arguing about, like, what standards of conduct are, because they don't see, fundamentally, it's that...
[SPEAKER_04]: Whether you're acting out of greed, aversion and aversion or not, and that's not going to manifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same way, for everyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if someone comes here, and they ask you, what is right effort?
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha talks about right effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, what would you say?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's maintenance of the non-acting out, based on seeing the mind, when there's a pull towards a particular sense object.
[SPEAKER_01]: And how are you making sure that it is the actual minds that you are seeing?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when somebody comes here, they've been reading some book, Introduction to Buddhism,
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, no wasteful path, right efforts.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm prepared to make efforts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can you please tell me what's right efforts?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you give that answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, can we assume that people immediately know what the mind is, and what we mean by pressure, for example?
[SPEAKER_01]: And if not, then, what would be the right answer?
[SPEAKER_01]: To the question, what's the right effort?
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, yeah, realistically, what would usually happen is, when the person starts to try to make effort, every thought is a pressure.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's going to feel like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's going to feel like everything is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything that...
[SPEAKER_01]: Eating a meal can come out of pressure, because I want to stay alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, from the beginning, if somebody is, like, serious, and you start out by saying, it might very well feel like they can't do anything.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so, but that's now the symptom that you should see that, well, something's wrong.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because if you follow that thread, the final outcome is you have to stop breathing.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, because everything you would do would be like, oh, why am I breathing?
[SPEAKER_04]: Do I have
[SPEAKER_04]: You might ask a question like, why am I breathing?
[SPEAKER_04]: Do I have something to live for in this life?
[SPEAKER_04]: You realize, no, okay, so that means I'm acting out of craving?
[SPEAKER_04]: But that's obviously not how it works, because the Buddha was not a jain.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, what is the mind then?
[SPEAKER_04]: What does it mean to be... for the mind to be affected by pressure, and for you to be acting out of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is indeed what determines right efforts from wrong efforts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you said is not wrong, but it's just that if that's the only thing we say, it will practically still probably not be right.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, because mind can mean anything for people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I would first not focus on symptoms, on particular
[SPEAKER_00]: From my point of view, pressures, particulars, objects, but only see rather this attitude of being labeled to pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, those symptoms, those particulars, wouldn't be there if there's this liability behind these particular symptoms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you have any symptoms?
[SPEAKER_00]: For example, mind under sloth and torpor, hindrance.
[SPEAKER_00]: But is that a symptom or is that the... it's like background from particular manifestations of it?
[SPEAKER_04]: But what is, let's say, what is this love and torpor?
[SPEAKER_04]: Is it just the fact that you don't have energy?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Particular direction towards getting sleepy.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically lack of energy.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's, of course, manifesting somehow, bodily, mentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: And those are the symptoms of
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you said you don't focus on the symptoms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Symptoms are there because, of course, there's a bigger problem behind them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, they couldn't be there.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, then, if you have a mind that's sleepy or tired,
[SPEAKER_04]: Do you try to get rid of the sleep or tiredness, or what do you do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Endure on the right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not acting out, not getting into it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Factually, when there's pressure to go to sleep, I won't go to sleep at that very moment.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, but as you said, enduring on the right level, how would that manifest?
[SPEAKER_04]: By not acting out, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, but...
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, of course, you don't, eh... go to sleep.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the obvious part, but... eh... if you're not doing that, you could still be fundamentally trying to get rid of the sleepiness.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you would still have that kind of, ehm... underlying... wish that this will go away.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which means, you still kind of put the emphasis on the symptom.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, how would you make sure that truly, truly, you see, okay, this is just a symptom and I'm not going to be concerned with this?
[SPEAKER_00]: It might be like, let's say, that you say no to go to the sleep, but you can easily end up directing towards something else with the same attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when, at the same time, I'm
[SPEAKER_00]: The direction towards particulars, sleepiness, and basically any other activity body, that I already can maintain not acting out.
[SPEAKER_04]: But wait, so is that... you're saying that any other bodily activity you would do would be rooted in sleep pressure?
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bodily activity that... it's...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, let's say, could you just get up and start walking?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, because, let's say, that walking would be rooted on the same mind, kind of.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, although I don't go to sleep, I find some other, like, external bodily activity
[SPEAKER_01]: What's wrong with that?
[SPEAKER_01]: If that prevents you, like if you splash cold water on your face, or you switch on the light in order to prevent falling asleep, which requires action on your part, if that prevents you from giving in to the sleepiness, then why do you say that that bodily activity is necessarily coming out of the same attitude?
[SPEAKER_00]: For example,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the sleepiness is manifested when I sit down.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when I, of course, going to lay down, it's like lower.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going towards that sleepiness.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, say, when I stay now, it's the same attitude for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, I'd rather remain seated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not changing any position, just
[SPEAKER_00]: So, from that point of view, I do not make any movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Towards, or away, or replace it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But how do you know that that is also not going under that same attitude?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I shouldn't now move?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I maintain the knowledge of that mind is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But are you saying that I
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you know that the mental state that would be behind getting up and walking is not actually a new state that is... well, it's rooted specifically in not giving in to the other state?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, because it sounds like you're saying that if you necessarily, if you got up, it would be rooted in the pressure, but
[SPEAKER_00]: And at the moment when I realized that this this pressure of going to the sleep is no longer there, it kind of energy manifested, because of the knowledge that this mind is also no longer there.
[SPEAKER_00]: This pressure, this manifestation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, this entire momentum at this very moment
[SPEAKER_04]: But does that mean that then you need to get rid of it in order to have that energy?
[SPEAKER_00]: What I'm trying to say, I need to do anything, rather than just realize that the state of mind is there and not going towards this direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all what I need to do.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, but the thing is that the thing of the decision to stay seated and not do anything,
[SPEAKER_04]: That can also be a form of action.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, it's not that automatically, because you don't get up, like, you might still be doing that out of craving.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, whether the thing goes away or it stays, that's secondary, because fundamentally, you're still maintaining yourself alive.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, that would be the momentum.
[SPEAKER_04]: The momentum would be that when pressure arises, you can't put up with it.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can only
[SPEAKER_04]: And so, like, enduring things on the right level, would mean, even if the pressure is there, you're not affected by it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So that even if you're... even if the mind is sleepy, you can
[SPEAKER_04]: Or the body is sleeping, whatever.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can distance yourself from it and see this has arisen on its own.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, like, it's impossible to have a permanent state of energy.
[SPEAKER_04]: And even in suttas, it would say the basis for sloth and torpor
[SPEAKER_04]: is tiredness, sleepiness, sluggishness after the meal, but the hindrance of sloth and torpor is the wrong attention, ayoniso manasikāra, that you would pay to the state of tiredness, drowsiness, and so on.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you were to get up, but not with
[SPEAKER_04]: That, let's say, like you said, that attitude of expecting or hoping that the pressure of tiredness will go away, then that's the right level.
[SPEAKER_04]: That would be the right level.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if you think, I need to get this to to go away somehow,
[SPEAKER_04]: Whether by staying seated or getting up, fundamentally, that is the problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like the expectation or the hope to pretty much change something that wasn't yours to begin with.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, like the peace that you want to discover and become established in,
[SPEAKER_04]: It is the peace of not being bothered by it in the first place, not the peace of, like, I get it to go away and then I'm fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because fundamentally, the mind, like the citta, it's not the... it's not that when you have, let's say, a lustful mind,
[SPEAKER_04]: There will always be that tendency to confuse lustful mind with the thoughts that come on account of the lustful mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the natural tendency is to look at the problem there and then think, okay, if I can just get this to go away, by any means necessary,
[SPEAKER_04]: Do a concentration technique.
[SPEAKER_04]: Look somewhere else.
[SPEAKER_04]: Think about something else.
[SPEAKER_04]: Replace it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Ignore it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then the lust is gone.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: But the lust is that liability, so that if those, let's say, images or thoughts were to present themselves, you can't be... you can't stay distanced from them.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's the same with the sloth and torpor.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like,
[SPEAKER_04]: Svatantorpor is not the presence of that pressure of tiredness.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's, as you said, the liability.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's the fact that if the body gets tired, if there is sluggishness, the mind gets mixed and involved with it.
[SPEAKER_04]: It can't stay distanced from it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's what... that's the right level.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, it's the... it's the recognition that these things arise on their own.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that the mind, the citta, that you have to tame, is that basically like that... almost feel... it would feel almost like automatic.
[SPEAKER_04]: Engagement with these pressures that come up.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, that's why it's called like the opening amidst confinement.
[SPEAKER_04]: When the siddhas would talk about the right view and even samādhi.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it's not that you get rid of the confinement.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you get rid of these, let's say, unpleasant things that might be assailing you.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're getting rid of your craving in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's the Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, suffering is not the sleepiness, it's not the the lust, like, the the sign of beauty, it's not the annoyance of, like, the significance of other people or other situations being annoying.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's the craving that then, far down the line, leads you to act out of lust, act out of anger, act out of
[SPEAKER_04]: You go to sleep out of laziness, but that's that's now, like, it's not that then if I just... if I just get rid of those things, it's only really like I'm undoing the... it's like a, like, instead of, let's say, some object that you have on the ground, instead of hammering it fixed onto the ground, like, nailing it down so that it doesn't move,
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter what comes, you just stop things from coming.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's only ever going to be temporary.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, that cannot be a reliable freedom.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's why it would keep coming back.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, it would feel like, every time these things come back up, I need to deal with them again, and again, and again.
[SPEAKER_04]: Whereas, what you really want to see is, how do I make myself not be liable, so that whether this comes up or not,
[SPEAKER_04]: It's completely irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, what I meant is rather the mere fact of this choice of
[SPEAKER_00]: Once again, without intention to kind of change that state and to get rid of it or whatever, just recognizing that at this particular time, at this particular occasion, there's no acting out, the choice of not giving in, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there's a need to go away.
[SPEAKER_04]: There wasn't that intention at all.
[SPEAKER_04]: But is there still like a sort of
[SPEAKER_04]: view or emphasis that if it doesn't go away, I haven't succeeded.
[SPEAKER_04]: Would you be able to see that if it stays there for 10 years, there's no problem?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or would you feel like, hmm, something's still missing?
[SPEAKER_00]: I can tell it was just the recognition that the victory, the small victory of not acting out of this mind at this very moment.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, but that's it.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think that it's not acting out, but the not acting out of the right level, fundamentally, depends on whether you see, like, it doesn't matter whether this stays or leaves, because my responsibility is the craving, not the feeling.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, even if it remains kind of assailing you, for whatever amount of time, you need to reach that certainty that I'm safe here, regardless of what comes up.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because then, I see, if you then, if there's that, that, at least that's what you said, it sounded to me like you're saying, oh, the victory came when the thing went away.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no, no, this is not like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: So when, what is the victory then?
[SPEAKER_04]: The recognition of that state and not going to sleep.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a remote, basically, old habit of escaping, going.
[SPEAKER_02]: Surely, then, what if there comes a point when you can't go?
[SPEAKER_04]: You could go to sleep, no?
[SPEAKER_04]: You wouldn't necessarily be acting out of a certain door.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, you could.
[SPEAKER_04]: You could go to sleep.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because otherwise, every arahant who went to sleep would be acting out of a hidden switch.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, let alone getting up as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not claiming the sleepiness as if and basically itself, but at this particular instance, it was rooted in hindrance.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, no, of course.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, there would be a hindrance involved, but I'm just saying, like, it's important to keep the emphasis, because it's going to happen.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not a matter of if.
[SPEAKER_04]: That that kind of view will set back in that I'm fine only when it goes away.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it's not it's not something that you will kind of necessarily tell yourself.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like to the extent that you feel any sense of vulnerability to suffering, it's because to some extent there's still that desire or that expectation to control that which is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, if that was clarified enough that that actually isn't the problem, then you wouldn't even reach the point where the suffering comes up and then you need to kind of not act out and get it to go away.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can tell it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: And therefore, it's like clouds of... clouds that are obstructing this knowledge that the mind is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like constant... this habit is like waves.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every time acting out, it
[SPEAKER_00]: Lack of knowledge, what mine is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But this particular event, it's like reminder that not acting out equals freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, therefore, it's like breaking the chain of automatic habits, of the all habits of acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in what sense are they automatic?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, basically, constant choice of acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Constant choice of acting out?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Choice, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's choice.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, eh... like, how can the choice... Are you saying the choice happens by itself?
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: Basically, it's...
[SPEAKER_04]: Right.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, then, that's what I'm trying to say.
[SPEAKER_04]: Decisions of acting out, it's...
[SPEAKER_04]: The wave... You cannot say that the wave is a habit.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because the habit would be, kind of, your...
[SPEAKER_04]: Engagement with that thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: Rather, if any way that might come, in and of itself, is not the issue.
[SPEAKER_04]: Habit of choosing acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the habit of choosing acting out, but the habit is on you, not on something else that comes by itself.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's, like, the point is, it might sound like the same thing, but if there's that implication of, like, I'm being almost, like, compromised or threatened by these things that come on their own,
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, that's not the right level.
[SPEAKER_04]: The right level means recognizing, actually, it doesn't matter what comes.
[SPEAKER_04]: I cannot be threatened, except through my own choice.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's what the...
[SPEAKER_04]: But then, if... Again, like...
[SPEAKER_04]: When there's that implication, it's usually not going to be recognized.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's something that you have to kind of...
[SPEAKER_04]: Not assume that just saying, okay, I just don't act out.
[SPEAKER_04]: You also have to investigate, because sometimes not acting out will not be the right level.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, it won't be seen on the right level, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: It will still have that implication of like, okay, I don't act out, so that it goes away.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then the victory, um...
[SPEAKER_04]: Again, just repeat.
[SPEAKER_04]: It would have nothing to do with whether the thing went away or not.
[SPEAKER_04]: The victory would be just recognizing the level where you're not affected, no matter what comes up.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, if you recognize that level, you would see that it doesn't matter whether you get up or stay seated, because that's not automatically
[SPEAKER_04]: What it means to act out.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like you yourself said, it's an attitude.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, attitude is a mental decision.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not like just simply because I stood up, it meant that I acted out of craving.
[SPEAKER_04]: Same as eating.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even when you're hungry, for that matter.
[SPEAKER_04]: Eating when you're hungry doesn't mean that you are acting out of craving.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like you have that reflection of I will eat only for the sake of
[SPEAKER_04]: Nourishing the body not for the sake of entertainment.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, in the same way, you could say, okay, I'll get up not for the sake of fighting with the sleepiness.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm fine if this stays for the next 20 years.
[SPEAKER_04]: But I will not do this because I want it to go away.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that that little kind of implication is something that's up to you.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not up to the action that you do.
[SPEAKER_04]: Of course, if you break the precepts, the implication will always be wrong.
[SPEAKER_04]: But
[SPEAKER_04]: Putting that aside, you could do almost an endless amount of things, not with the underlying motivation or hope that's affected by craving.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's how you would actually be free.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not that you kind of need to constrict yourself more and more to do less and less things because you don't act out.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you recognize actually acting out
[SPEAKER_04]: is a mental choice.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, you realize, like, you have that huge range of things that won't be involving you with the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, attitude of
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's like... but it's a mental emphasis.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a mental direction.
[SPEAKER_04]: In this case, to again use that example of sleepiness, it's
[SPEAKER_04]: Usually, it's going to be that hope.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you could even be saying, oh, this has arisen on its own.
[SPEAKER_04]: This is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_04]: This is just a bodily state.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm not going to be affected by it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you're saying all that, because at the back of your mind, still, you're affected.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you're
[SPEAKER_04]: Taking it for granted and hoping for it to go away.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's a... it's... but it's a... it's a... it's... it will take drilling, because one thing is to hear that information and... and, like, it makes sense, but then, eh... again, you could be saying that, like, oh, okay, I...
[SPEAKER_04]: I...
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm gonna try to practice on the right level.
[SPEAKER_04]: I won't try to get rid of it, because I heard that that's what I have to do.
[SPEAKER_04]: Still, that's not what the... that's not immediately the solution.
[SPEAKER_04]: The solution is, when you actually see that full extent of craving, that full extent of the acting out, and you see, oh wait, actually, this doesn't happen by accident.
[SPEAKER_04]: This isn't just like, oh, it came by itself and it took over.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like me overlooking that, you could say, yeah, attitude, inclination, tendency.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just not seeing and taking it for granted.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the habit.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not like the habit is the specific, like going to sleep or doing this or doing that.
[SPEAKER_04]: The habit is when pressure manifests,
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't even see where the line is, and you either indulge in it, or you try to get rid of it, because you think that that's what the problem is.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's a fundamental habit of ignorance.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not like... that the other things might just completely be neutral, like habits of specific things that you might be used to doing, but... when... like the habit of craving is on that much more subtle level of how you relate
[SPEAKER_04]: To pressure as such, as a general phenomenon, regardless of its particulars.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's why you can have sometimes even like a... there might not be anything going on.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like you might have a neutral feeling, let's say.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're not particularly pulled by sensuality, aversion, sleepiness, anxiety or doubt.
[SPEAKER_04]: But there's that kind of inactivity, kind of lack of anything going on.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that is a pressure in itself.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, because somebody might be expecting like, oh, it's only these very kind of blatant, in-my-face, super unwholesome things.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, if that's not there, then it's like, okay, well, nothing's happening.
[SPEAKER_04]: But no.
[SPEAKER_04]: That same pressure of sensuality, whatever, it's the same kind of principle that's there of that when the neutral feeling is there.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just a... you could say a feeling that you either overlook, take for granted, take as yours, act out of in whichever direction, or you don't.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's why it's... that's why I said that if you know the neutral feeling,
[SPEAKER_04]: It's it's going to be pleasant.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you don't know it, it's going to be unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but I would say this is already somewhat of an accomplishment to factually even recognize a neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would have to already have not acted out of of pretty much most of the hindrances, like... Yeah, because somebody can say, oh, there's these three kinds of feeling, and then they might designate all sorts of things and they derive a neutral feeling, but that's overwhelmingly possibly wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that would hinge, well, not only on the on the on the virtue and restraint now, but also on seclusion, in order to start recognizing these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the other thing, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, back when we were asking about the right efforts, and you were talking about seeing the mind, like, are you going to see that, like, outside of seclusion?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you are, right, always surrounded by people, then is that, will that ever be clear?
[SPEAKER_01]: But you designated as a mind earlier.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then, if somebody asks what is right effort, you can say all of this, but you do not make it clear that they should put themselves in a situation of
[SPEAKER_01]: Or at least have a fair amount of hours where you are just physically on your own.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's going to be a necessary condition in order to even see that might.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't see that, then everything that we just discussed will remain abstract.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, but even just more...
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't think most people are at the stage where what they need is actually seclusion.
[SPEAKER_04]: You go to seclusion without the foundation of the precepts well established and it's not really
[SPEAKER_04]: That's not going to lead to the right thing, because your acting out now is on a much more coarse level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I was going to come to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I was actually walking backwards from what he is saying to the seclusion, and then the next step was actually going to be, in order for you to hold that seclusion, where there's no fulfilling, like boredom, or perhaps some sense of loneliness, or right?
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's going to come up, and in order to now not be overwhelmed by that, it's going to be possible only if you already know how to deal with the more coarse acting out, which is on the level of the basic precepts now.
[SPEAKER_04]: There's just no way that you can begin to see, like, what does it mean for the mind to resist a neutral feeling, if the full-on sensual pleasure and happiness, you immediately jump at it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Aversion, like unpleasant feeling, when it manifests, when people say things that you don't like, things that are unpleasant for you, you immediately react, try to kind of get them to not say that, or tell them off, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_04]: There's just no hope, like you're completely out there, and this stuff is like under the radar.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're not going to see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, we can also make a connection here, like, you know, because it's in a sense easier to recognize that acting out of anger and ill will and hate speech, whether it's online or elsewhere, right, that all of that is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you say to someone that it would be good if people, including yourself, do less of that, then most people will agree.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, what is often not seen, is that if, at the same time, you still act out of the desire for sensuality, then that is just going to be a hollow statement.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, why is that so?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, when there is a sensual impulse coming up, and you don't recognize that, and you act out, there's basically no space between you and that mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if that space is not there, there's just a life of habitual sensual gratification, instant gratification.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, when there's an unpleasant feeling, there's also going to be no space.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, there will be an immediate acting out, trying to get rid of the thing that you think is making you feel unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, the connection is that it is that same mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if somebody factually wants to bring about a situation where there is not going to be any acting out of ill will,
[SPEAKER_01]: Suppose they have that intention, then that's good and you should restrain acting out of that aversion and that annoyance and that hatred and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're going to be very quickly running into a wall if you do not simultaneously start also restraining sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is what not so many people are prepared to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that means that this is a hollow statement to then only deal with the aversion and the ill will in isolation from the sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, it's not necessarily that you will
[SPEAKER_04]: You may be acting out of aversion just because you give in to sensuality, but you will fall into, then, the superficial management and psychotherapy techniques.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, then, you will not be... you may not be angry with other people, you know, you will not be expressing your anger, but that internal kind of spark of... the thing coming up in the first place, this discontent or this
[SPEAKER_04]: Annoyance coming up in the first place.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's not going to change, because it's... that's... yeah, like you said, it's maintained by the sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you are bothered by things not going your way, because you want things to go your way.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because you... you're used to chasing your way.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's precisely what desire and sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you didn't have that, as we said before, you didn't have your way that you're chasing,
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, why would you be bothered when things don't blow your way?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.